<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Catalysis of the transesterification reaction can be roughly divided into two categories, chemical and enzymatic. Chemical catalyzed transesterification reactions can be carried out by either acid or base, in homogeneous or heterogeneous phase, and selection of the conditions depends on the characteristic of the starting triacylglycerides. Basic catalysts are usually preferred to acid catalysts because they provide better reaction rates, lower temperature requirements, and higher conversion efficiencies. NaOH and KOH are classical catalysts, although sodium methoxide derived from the added NaOH is actually the most applied at industrial scale. The protocol involves the dissolution of the catalyst in methanol by vigorous stirring, and mixing the resulting alcohol/catalyst solution with the vegetable oil to give two liquid phases (biodiesel and glycerol) with high yields (&gt;90%) after several hours at 65&#8211;90 &#176;C. However, when the free fatty acids (FFAs) content of the triglycerides is higher than 1&#8211;2% w/w, basic catalysts can also produce saponification as a side reaction. In such cases, acid catalysts (e.g., H<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>) are used, but of large amounts of alcohol (e.g., a molar excess of alcohol over the vegetable oil higher up to 10) and the complete removal of free water are required. Homogeneous catalysts usually give better results than heterogeneous catalysts for biodiesel production. However, many problems are associated with homogeneous catalysis, such as high energy consumption, the formation of unwanted soap by-products because of the presence of FFAs, expensive catalyst separation from the reaction mixture, and specially the generation of large amounts of wastewater during products separation and cleaning. These are clear breakdown points for the sustainability of homogeneous basic catalysis, the usual approach applied at industrial scale for producing biofuel. In contrast, the use of solid acids (e.g., sulfonic acid resins, sulfonic acid-modified silica, <italic>etc.</italic>), or solid bases (e.g., BaO, SrO, MgO, KNO<sub>3</sub>/Al<sub>2</sub>O<sub>3</sub>, <italic>etc.</italic>), as heterogeneous catalysts permits their easy separation from reaction mixture by simple filtration, enabling recycling [<xref rid="B3-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="B4-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p>