<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">The thermal stability of fatty acid methyl esters and biodiesel prepared by non-catalytic SCFs methods and obtained from various plant oils has been studied over a wide range of high temperatures (270&#8211;430 &#176;C) and pressures (17&#8211;56 MPa) in order to evaluate the effect of the harsh experimental conditions on the biodiesel fuel quality [<xref rid="B35-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="B36-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. It was found that although all fatty acid methyl esters, including the poly-unsaturated ones, are stable at low temperatures and pressures, but they partially decomposed with isomerization from <italic>cis</italic>-olefin to <italic>trans</italic>-olefin at high pressure and temperature. From these results, it was suggested that, for high-quality biodiesel production, the reaction temperatures in SCFs processes should be maintained below 300 &#176;C, preferably at 270 &#176;C for supercritical methanol (scMeOH), and lower than 360 &#176;C for supercritical methyl acetate (scMeOAc) with a supercritical pressure higher than 8.09 MPa (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-17-08696-f003">Figure 3</xref>). Besides, higher temperatures increase energy consumption and thus operating costs. However, it has been suggested that by selecting the adequate experimental conditions, processing could use less energy than the conventional method. Justification for this claim was based on the absence of the need for catalyst addition and energy intensive purification operations (distillation), making this technology economically competitive with the conventional ones [<xref rid="B37-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. As regards reactor design, although batch biodiesel production is favoured over continuous processes in many research laboratories and in large scale operations, continuous operation is expected to gain wider acceptance, considering their added advantages that include a higher production capacity and lower operating costs to ensure the long term supply of biodiesel. Additionally, key parameters such as oil concentration in the supercritical phase, and the density of the mixture (depending on temperature, pressure and composition) can be easily controlled and optimized under flow conditions [<xref rid="B38-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B39-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B40-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="B41-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p>