<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para0033">Analysis of the spent catalyst was studied after reusability and recyclability to depict its morphological characteristic by BET and the effect of reaction on the CaO by XRD. Observation showed that the S<sub>BET</sub> (Surface area) and the total pore volume increased as the reusability continued, while the basic site (BS), the total basic site (TBS), and the basic site density (BSD) of the spent catalyst decreased (<xref rid="tbl0010" ref-type="table">Table&#160;10</xref>). This is an indication that catalyst recyclability, purification, and reusability decreased the basic strength of the catalyst during the reaction process. The main aim of catalyst regeneration is targeted at restoring the high surface area and high dispersal of the element in the catalysts <xref rid="bib0026" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. Furthermore, the effect of leaching within the reactor can easily lead to coverage of active surface sites hereby decreasing the biodiesel yield. The results displayed by XRD analysis alongside with the BET displayed that the percentage decrease to (25.43%) in CaO derived from CWWA was very high after reusability and regeneration. It was observed that the percentage of CaO decreased from 62.83% to 25.43%.<table-wrap position="float" id="tbl0010"><label>Table 10</label><caption><p>Characteristic of a spent CWWA.</p></caption><alt-text id="alt0015">Table 10</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top">Catalyst</th><th valign="top">N<sub>2</sub>-AA(m<sup>2</sup>g<sup>&#8722;1</sup>)</th><th valign="top">TPV(cm<sup>3</sup>g<sup>&#8722;1</sup>)</th><th valign="top">%CaO</th><th colspan="2" align="left" valign="top">BS (&#956;mole.g<sup>&#8722;1</sup>)400&lt;BS&lt;500 &gt;500</th><th valign="top">TBS</th><th valign="top">BSD (&#956;mole/m<sup>2</sup>)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top"><italic>CWWA</italic></td><td valign="top">1.40</td><td valign="top">0.0080</td><td valign="top">25. 43</td><td valign="top">&#8211;</td><td valign="top">86.00</td><td valign="top">86.00</td><td valign="top">61.43</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>N<sub>2</sub>-AA= nitrogen adsorption analysis, TPV&#160;=&#160;Total pore volume, BS&#160;=&#160;Basic site, TBS&#160;=&#160;Total basic site, BSD&#160;=&#160;Basic site density.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>