<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Many free and immobilized microbial lipases have been tested as catalysts of the synthesis of biodiesel [<xref rid="B9-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In the last years, enzymes like <italic toggle="yes">Candida antarctica</italic> lipase A (Cal A) [<xref rid="B37-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] and very specially Eversa Transform<sup>&#174;</sup>, a genetically-modified variant of the lipase from <italic toggle="yes">Thermomyces lanuginosus</italic> designed by Novozymes for the synthesis of biodiesel, have been used in this application [<xref rid="B36-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,<xref rid="B38-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,<xref rid="B39-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B40-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>,<xref rid="B41-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>,<xref rid="B42-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Both biocatalysts have been immobilized by hydrophobicity on octyl agarose beads [<xref rid="B24-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B39-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>,<xref rid="B43-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], Cal A was also covalently attached to chitosan-coated magnetic nanoparticles activated with GA [<xref rid="B44-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>], and mCLEAs of Eversa Transform<sup>&#174;</sup> were prepared and tested to produce biodiesel [<xref rid="B41-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. The recombinant versatile lipase from <italic toggle="yes">Ophiostoma piceae</italic> (OPEr) has shown to be a robust biocatalyst, whose activity is maintained or improved upon immobilization. The activity and efficiency of various preparations with immobilized OPEr have been previously tested in two reactions of industrial interest: the synthesis of flavors by direct esterification (in biphasic systems) [<xref rid="B45-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], and the production of sterol esters by transesterification in a solvent-free medium [<xref rid="B31-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. In this work, we will present the results of biodiesel production from methanol and cooking oil wastes by a green procedure. Six variants with immobilized OPEr are evaluated as catalysts of the reaction, performed at room temperature (25 &#176;C) without adding water or cosolvent. The enzyme is covalently immobilized on nanoparticles of magnetite bearing superficial amino or aldehyde groups, as well as non-covalently (by hydrophobic interaction) on a magnetic support with octyl groups in the surface. A novel Zn/Mn oxide without magnetic properties is also tested as an immobilization scaffold after being functionalized with amino or aldehyde groups. The results are compared with those shown by the free OPEr and the commercial lipases Eversa<sup>&#174;</sup> and Cal A<sup>&#174;</sup>.</p>