<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">The examination of Sg-CN and starting material graphitic carbon nitride (g-CN) reveals the crystalline nature of Sg-CN which is reaffirmed by comparing the XRD pattern of Sg-CN and g-CN (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3a</xref>). The stability of the catalyst and temperature tolerance have been studied using thermogravimetric analysis (TGA), which confirms that the synthesized sulfonated graphitic carbon nitride is stable up 250&#8201;&#176;C (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Fig. 3b</xref>). The change in functional group and electronic behavior has been studied using FTIR and solid state <sup>13</sup>C-NMR. Juxtapose of FT-IR and <sup>13</sup>C-NMR spectra of g-CN and Sg-CN corroborate the presence of essential functionality differences and electronic nature (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary</xref>) as evidenced by the peak at 1200&#8201;cm<sup>&#8722;1</sup> a characteristic signal for sulfonated graphitic carbon nitride (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S4</xref>) which is confirmed by comparative analysis of <sup>13</sup>C-NMR of g-CN and Sg-CN (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S5</xref>) The BET surface analysis of g-CN (35.42&#8201;m<sup>2</sup>/g, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S5</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S6</xref>) and Sg-CN (10.04&#8201;m<sup>2</sup>/g, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S7</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Fig. S8</xref>) also confirmed the immobilization of sulfonic group. There is sharp decline in the surface area after the immobilization which is may be due to the creation of ionic character on the nitrogenous framework of g-CN culminating in the better interlayer attraction in graphitic carbon nitride.</p>