<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The concentrated enzyme crude containing the recombinant lipase from <italic toggle="yes">O. piceae</italic> was immobilized by several procedures. The SiMAG-octyl scaffold used for non-covalent (hydrophobic) immobilization bears an octyl (C8) surface group and was provided by Chemicell (Berlin, Germany). All other functionalized supports were prepared in the laboratory using commercial Fe<sub>3</sub>O<sub>4</sub> magnetic nanoparticles (MNPs) or a new type of non-magnetic nanoparticles, whose formula is Zn<sub>0.25</sub>Mn<sub>2.75</sub>O<sub>4</sub> (G1). This carrier was synthesized using material recovered from discarded alkaline batteries, and its preparation and purification have been described elsewhere [<xref rid="B47-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>]. The magnetic nanoparticles were characterized by X-ray diffraction, scanning and transmission electron microscopy and Fourier transform infrared spectroscopy under conditions previously reported [<xref rid="B45-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], using the same methods to characterize the G1 non-magnetic carrier. All scaffolds were coated with a thin layer of Si and amino groups were incorporated on their surface (AMNP and AG1 carriers) by treatment with 99% (3-aminopropyl)triethoxysilane (APTS, Sigma-Aldrich), followed or not by activation with glutaraldehyde [<xref rid="B45-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. If activated, the carriers are denominated as AMNP-GA and AG1-GA. The crudes with OPEr were immobilized by four procedures: (i) For immobilization by adsorption, the protein solution was carefully mixed with SiMAG-octyl nanoparticles in 100 mM Tris-HCl buffer pH 7 [<xref rid="B45-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] to produce the catalyst SiMAG-octyl-OPEr; (ii) covalent attachment to AMNP-GA or AG1-GA was attained by mixing the protein solution with the activated carrier in 100 mM Tris-HCl buffer solution, pH 7 [<xref rid="B45-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. These catalysts were denominated AMNP-GA-OPEr and AG1-GA-OPEr; (iii) magnetic cross-linked enzyme aggregates (mCLEAs-OPEr) were prepared in the presence of the activated carrier AMNP-GA by precipitation with ammonium sulfate and crosslinking with GA in 100 mM Tris-HCl buffer solution, pH 7 [<xref rid="B45-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]; (iv) for immobilization through the carbohydrate chains, the protein solutions were first subjected to a soft oxidation with NaIO<sub>4</sub> to produce aldehyde groups from vicinal diols in the sugar chain. Then, the solution was allowed to react with AMNPs or AG1 under reducing conditions, stabilizing the covalent linkage with NaBH<sub>4</sub> [<xref rid="B31-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. These catalysts were denominated AMNP-CH-OPEr and AG1-CH-OPEr.</p>