<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">It has recently been demonstrated that biodiesel can be produced from triglycerides and dimethyl carbonate instead of methanol, in a non-catalytic process by using supercritical dimethyl carbonate (T<sub>c</sub> = 274.9 &#176;C, p<sub>c</sub> = 4.6 MPa) [<xref rid="B63-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>,<xref rid="B64-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>,<xref rid="B65-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. In this way, triglycerides as well as fatty acids are successfully converted to fatty acid methyl esters (FAMEs). Besides, with this methodology another valuable compound, glycerol carbonate, is obtained as a secondary product, instead of the undesirable glycerol, and a weak acid, such as citramalic acid, as the main by-product (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-17-08696-f003">Figure 3</xref>). Glycerol carbonate has a higher commercial value compared than glycerol and has a greater potential for industrial application [<xref rid="B66-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. Hence, this methodology could have a large impact on biodiesel economics as two high added value products are produced in a single-step reaction, leading to increases cost effectiveness, even if high temperatures and pressures are required. The FAMEs produced by this method are obtained at higher yields than with supercritical methanol, and satisfy the international standards for use as biodiesel fuel. For instance, up to a 97.4 wt% yield can be obtained for the scDMC method at 300 &#176;C, 20 MPa, 20 min and a 42:1 molar ratio of dimethyl carbonate to oil [<xref rid="B67-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The properties of the biodiesel produced by this method have been evaluated according to different international standards. Overall, the FAMEs from the scDMC method satisfied all the requirements for international biodiesel standards except the specification regarding oxidation stability, which is an important parameter for preventing deterioration. However, this problem could be diminished by the addition of an antioxidant or by using oils containing lower levels of unsaturated fatty acids [<xref rid="B68-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>].</p>