<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Investigation of the phase behaviour of the reaction system is important for better understanding the enzymatic synthesis of biodiesel in supercritical fluids. Pressure and temperature can affect the reaction rate by affecting the partitioning of the reaction components between the two phases, leading to poor conversions at the enzyme surface. Thus, Ciftci <italic>et al.</italic> studied the phase behaviour of corn oil-methanol-CO<sub>2</sub> mixtures as a function of pressure by using a phase equilibrium cell equipped with a sapphire window [<xref rid="B77-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. Visual observation of the phase behaviour of the reaction mixture upon pressurization at 55 &#176;C showed that the immiscible biphasic liquid phase, consisting of corn oil and methanol, approached a single liquid phase at pressures above the critical pressure of CO<sub>2</sub> and also expanded through the dissolution of CO<sub>2</sub>. However, as a single homogeneous phase was not fully formed at the pressure levels investigated in this study (11.0, 20.0 and 35.0 MPa), authors consider reaction mixture as a two phase (lower single liquid phase and upper CO<sub>2</sub> phase) system. Other authors studied the solubility of olive husk oil in scCO<sub>2</sub> (40&#8211;80 &#176;C, 15.0&#8211;35.0 MPa), and the influence of methanol and ethanol (1&#8211;5% v/v) as cosolvents, by using a dynamic flow method. It was observed how the solubility of the triglyceride increased moderately when increasing the CO<sub>2</sub> pressure at constant temperature, but doubled when 5% (v/v) of cosolvents was added [<xref rid="B78-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. The phase behaviour of the CO<sub>2</sub>-biodiesel system in the presence of cosolvents (e.g., methanol [<xref rid="B79-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">79</xref>], ethanol [<xref rid="B80-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">80</xref>], <italic>etc.</italic>) has also been studied, leading to the observation that the addition of alcohol improves their miscibility.</p>