<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">Barreiros and co-workers [<xref rid="B84-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">84</xref>] implemented a continuous process for biodiesel production in supercritical carbon dioxide by using virgin sunflower oil and methanol as substrates, which were incorporated in the reactor using a static mixer with 27 elements (See <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-17-08696-f007">Figure 7</xref>). The application of Lipozyme TL IM as biocatalyst led to FAMEs yields that exceeded 98% at 20.0 MPa and 40 &#176;C, for a residence time of 20 s and an oil to methanol molar ratio of 1:24. Even for moderate reaction conversions, a fractionation stage based on two high pressure cyclone separators provided FAMEs of up to 96% purity. In the same context, Dalla Rosa <italic>et al</italic> [<xref rid="B85-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>] reported the continuous production of fatty acid ethyl esters from soybean oil in compressed carbon dioxide, propane and <italic>n</italic>-butane, using immobilized Novozym 435 as the catalyst. The experiments were performed in a packed-bed bioreactor. An evaluation of the effects of pressure and temperature in the range of 5.0 to 15.0 MPa and 30&#8211;70 &#176;C, respectively, as well as the oil to ethanol molar ratio (from 1:6 to 1:18) and solvent to substrates mass ratio (from 4:1 to 10:1) was carried out. The best results (up to 98% yield) were obtained for lipase-catalyzed alcoholysis in a continuous tubular reactor using compressed propane (70 &#176;C, 6.0 MPa), which it is suggested as another potential route to biodiesel production. The similar dielectric constants of compressed propane and carbon dioxide, together with the higher pressure phase transition values generally found in systems formed by carbon dioxide and high molecular weight compounds (e.g., triglycerides)lead weight to the belief that propane may also be suitable as reaction medium for enzyme-catalyzed bioconversions [<xref rid="B29-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B86-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>].</p>