<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">As regards biocatalysis, proteins are noticeably insoluble in all SCFs, allowing easy recovery and reuse, while the gas-like diffusivity and low viscosity of SCFs enhance reactant mass-transport rates to the active site of enzymes [<xref rid="B18-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Lipases and esterases in scCO<sub>2</sub> are the most widely studied systems, due to the catalytic promiscuity of these enzymes towards hydrophobic substrates and the ability of this SCF to dissolve and transport hydrophobic compounds [<xref rid="B19-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The synthesis of aliphatic esters of different alkyl chain lengths by esterification and/or transesterification (e.g., by alcoholysis, acidolysis or inter-esterification) is a common approach to the production of terpenic flavour compounds (e.g., geranyl acetate) [<xref rid="B20-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>], and the valorisation of oils and fats (e.g., enrichment of acylglycerols with polyunsaturated fatty acids [<xref rid="B21-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]). Currently, the use of lipases for the asymmetric synthesis of esters is one of the most important tools for organic chemists, whereby the combination of the unique properties of scCO<sub>2</sub> with the catalytic excellence of lipases allows the kinetic resolution (KR) or (dynamic) kinetic resolution (DKR) of a large number of racemates (e.g., 1-phenylethanol [<xref rid="B22-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>], glycidol [<xref rid="B23-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>], <italic>etc.</italic>). However, it must be taken into account that CO<sub>2</sub> cannot be considered completely inert with regards to its interaction with proteins. The CO<sub>2</sub> forms carbamates with &#949;-amino groups of lysine residues placed on the enzyme surface, and lowers the pH of the aqueous layer around the enzyme, which can result in a significant decrease in the enzyme activity [<xref rid="B24-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="B25-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>].</p>