<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">The most important environmental factors affecting (bio)catalyst performance in SCFs are pressure, temperature and water content. Indeed, these parameters influence all mass-transfer phenomena and (bio)catalyst activity by changing the rate-limiting steps or modulating their selectivity [<xref rid="B29-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>,<xref rid="B30-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. As an example, the catalytic activity of immobilized lipase for butyl butyrate synthesis was exponentially increased by the drop in scCO<sub>2</sub> density accompanying different combinations of pressure and temperature [<xref rid="B27-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. In the same context, for the pressure range of 7.7 to 8.5 MPa, the changes in the conformation of lipase resulted in an increased rate of esterification reactions. Thus, Dhake <italic>et al</italic>. obtained good yields (up to 99%) for the enzymatic synthesis of several citronellyl esters at 45 &#176;C and 8.0 MPa [<xref rid="B31-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Temperature influences enzyme activity much more than pressure not only due to the usual increment in reaction rates at higher temperatures, but also because of enzyme thermodeactivation processes. The optimal temperature of enzymatic processes in SCFs is related with pressure as both control solvent properties [<xref rid="B29-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Water concentration also greatly influences enzyme activity because proteins require a specific amount of bound water molecules to be active. When the water content is too high or if the water is a product of the reaction in the supercritical medium, the resulting increased humidity may lead to enzyme deactivation. Thus, the actual amount of water needed is specific to each SCF-substrate-enzyme system, and must be maintained constant throughout the process [<xref rid="B32-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. </p>