<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" id="para0011">The base catalyst used for biodiesel synthesis is classified mainly as a homogeneous catalyst (hydroxide of Na/K) and heterogeneous catalyst (majorly from solid wastes). The work reported by Ozkan et&#160;al. <xref rid="bib0002" ref-type="bibr">[2]</xref> developed calcium oxide (CaO) from waste materials as a heterogeneous catalyst for the synthesis of biodiesel, while <xref rid="bib0003" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref> employed the use of bio-based catalyst from cocoa pod husk as a heterogeneous catalyst for biodiesel production. Ogunkunle et&#160;al. <xref rid="bib0004" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> reported the production of biodiesel using both catalysts. The work of <xref rid="bib0005" ref-type="bibr">[5]</xref> produces biodiesel with the help of a heterogeneous catalyst, while <xref rid="bib0006" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref> described the use of a heterogeneous catalyst in the optimization of the production of rubber seed/palm oil biodiesel, IDI diesel engine performance, and emissions. Milano et&#160;al. <xref rid="bib0007" ref-type="bibr">[7]</xref> further used heterogeneous catalysts for the conversion of waste cooking oil-Calophyllum inophyllum to biodiesel, but the work reported by Nath et&#160;al. <xref rid="bib0008" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref> utilized the green heterogeneous base catalysts as an effective bio-based for the conversion of oil to biodiesel. Papasanee et&#160;al. <xref rid="bib0009" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref> reported a novel process for biodiesel production from slum sludge whereas <xref rid="bib0010" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref> studies the use of catalyst derived from cotton stalk for production of biodiesel from Madhuca indica oil. In another study, Choksi et&#160;al. <xref rid="bib0011" ref-type="bibr">[11]</xref> reported the development of catalyst derived from palm-fruit-bunch for biodiesel. However, the conversion of a low-value industrial waste into biodiesel via a catalyst derived from brewery waste was reported by Saravanan et&#160;al. <xref rid="bib0012" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. The advantages of using heterogeneous catalysts include ease of recoverability and reusability, readily available, nontoxic, eco-friendly, and low cost <xref rid="bib0013" ref-type="bibr">[13</xref>,<xref rid="bib0014" ref-type="bibr">14]</xref>.</p>