<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">In the present work, we describe a simple dual bioimprinting strategy to increase the catalytic efficiency of <italic>Thermomyces lanuginosus</italic> lipase (TLL). TLL happens to be among the least expensive commercially available lipases. We have reported earlier that precipitation rather than lyophilization is a better strategy for &#8220;drying&#8221; (removal of bulk water) enzymes before these are placed in organic solvents <xref rid="bib0080" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0090" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0095" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. Such precipitates have been called enzyme precipitated and rinsed with propanol (EPRP) or more generally enzyme precipitated and rinsed with organic solvents (EPROS). The use of surfactants is known to activate lipases by opening of the &#8216;lid&#8217; on the active site <xref rid="bib0105" ref-type="bibr">[21]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>. Our approach is similar to the one described by earlier workers <xref rid="bib0115" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0120" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="bib0125" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref> wherein the enzyme was dried by lyophilization. In the current work the drying has been done by precipitation. In both approaches the dried enzyme has a highly rigid conformation which results in freezing the &#8220;induced conformation&#8221;. Recently, we have shown that EPROS of subtilisin prepared by precipitation with a substrate alcohol bioimprints the enzyme and increases its rate <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. The dual bioimprinting by incorporating an ester substrate could enhance the reaction rates even further <xref rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>. The dual bioimprinting strategy in the present instance consists of precipitating the lipase with a substrate alcohol in the presence of a surfactant. This led to a preparation imprinted with a substrate but in the open lid form. We also use a solvent free medium (the oil itself works as a reaction media and no additional organic solvent is added). This further reduces the cost and removes another &#8220;non green&#8221; component from the process.</p>