<p xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">In order to prevent the production of glycerol as a by-product, a process was designed using methyl acetate instead of methanol under supercritical conditions [<xref rid="B69-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The supercritical methyl acetate (scMeOAc) non-catalytic method converts triglycerides into fatty acid methyl esters (FAMEs) and triacetin, instead of glycerol. Furthermore, it has been discovered that there were no adverse effects on the main fuel characteristics when the molar ratio of methyl oleate to triacetin was 3:1, which corresponds to the theoretically derived mole ratio from the trans-esterification reaction of rapeseed oil with methyl acetate (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="molecules-17-08696-f004">Figure 4</xref>). Moreover, the addition of triacetin to methyl oleate improved the <italic>pour point</italic> (defined as the lowest temperature at which a fuel product will begin to flow), and triacetin has a high oxidation stability. Therefore, by defining biodiesel fuel as a mixture of methyl oleate and triacetin, the supercritical methyl acetate can lead to an improved yield (105%) of biodiesel fuel compared with the conventional process. However, this value is lower than the maximum recovery expected (125% yield) because of the breakdown at the required high temperatures of some unsaturated fatty acid methyl esters. Despite this, the scMeOAc method not only improves the quality of the biodiesel fuel but also minimizes the separation and purification steps, and therefore the energy required. Saka <italic>et al.</italic> [<xref rid="B70-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] have used various supercritical carboxylate esters to convert triglycerides into FAMEs and triacetin in the absence of any catalyst. The highest product yield was obtained with supercritical methyl acetate, 97.7 wt% considering a mixture of both FAMEs and triacetin as biodiesel fuel. The lower reactivity shown by other carboxylate esters seems to be related to the length of alkyl chains in the esters, e.g., the longer alkyl chains in both alcohol and acyl moieties of carboxylate esters provides the lowest product yields [<xref rid="B71-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>]. Banchero and co-workers [<xref rid="B72-molecules-17-08696" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] demonstrated that supercritical methyl acetate can be successfully used in the transesterification process of different vegetable oils to obtain biodiesel fuel. The process was suitable for edible, non-edible or waste oils, regardless of the FFA content which usually affects the conventional transesterification process at atmospheric pressure. All the examined oils reached complete conversion after 50 min at 345 &#176;C, 20 MPa and with a methyl acetate:oil molar ratio of 42:1. </p>