<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The development of anti-biofilm agents is therefore considered of major interest and represents an important strategy since non-biocidal molecules to avoid the rapid appearance of resistant mutants are highly valuable. Among bacteria, staphylococci are prevalent causes of biofilm-associated infections [
 <xref rid="B6-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In particular, 
 <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (
 <italic>S. aureus</italic>) is an opportunistic pathogen that can cause serious diseases in humans, ranging from skin and soft tissue infections to invasive infections of the bloodstream, heart, lungs and other organs [
 <xref rid="B7-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. In 2013, Nicholson et al. reported that 30% of U.S. population was colonized by 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> while 1.5% was found to be a carrier of methicillin-resistant 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MRSA), a major cause of healthcare-related infections responsible for a significant proportion of nosocomial infections worldwide. Recently in the U.S. deaths from MRSA infections have exceeded those from many other infectious diseases, including HIV/AIDS [
 <xref rid="B8-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. 
 <italic>Staphylococcus epidermidis</italic> (
 <italic>S. epidermidis</italic>), conventionally considered a commensal of human skin, can cause significant problems when breaching the epithelial barrier, especially during biofilm-associated infection of indwelling medical devices [
 <xref rid="B9-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Most diseases caused by 
 <italic>S. epidermidis</italic> exhibit a chronic profile and occur as device-related infections (such as intravascular catheter or prosthetic joint infections) and/or their complications [
 <xref rid="B10-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In view of the above scenario the scientific community is seeking for new agents endowed of anti-biofilm capabilities to fight 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> and 
 <italic>S epidermidis</italic> infections. Recently, several reports indicated in vitro efficacy of non-biocidal essential oils (EOs) as promising treatment to reduce bacterial biofilm production and prevent the inducing of drug resistance [
 <xref rid="B11-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In different applications, EOs have been found of some efficacy in reducing biofilm production of either 
 <italic>S. aureus</italic> standard strains or MRSA [
 <xref rid="B12-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. In other reports, EOs and some of their purified chemical components have also been proved to inhibit 
 <italic>S epidermidis</italic> biofilm production [
 <xref rid="B18-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-molecules-24-00890" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. 
</p>
