<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0050">Hydro distillation or steam distillation using a modified Clevenger light oil arm apparatus separated essential oil portion from the crude sample. It was shown that steam distillation method of extraction was the best by far compared to hexane solvent extraction as the extraction yields were around 2.5–3 times greater (
 <xref rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">Pellerin, 1991</xref>).100 g of dried ginger sample was transferred to a 1000 ml flat bottom flask. 500 ml of distilled water was transferred into the flask so that weight ratio of sample to water was 1:5 or 10:2 in solvent to feed (SF) ratio. This ratio was close to the solvent to feed ratio reported in a recent Indonesian study which concluded that 10:1.7 SF ratio was the optimum water to sample ratio for the extraction of maximum oil yields around 3.7% (w/w) (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">Azizah et al., 2019</xref>). Glass thermometer was immersed in the liquid portion via the secondary neck of the flat bottom flask. Using the heating mantel flask was heated to 70 °C and maintained in that temperature for 30 min. This ensured that the ginger pieces were soaked and saturated well before heated up evenly for the distillation process to begin. Then the temperature was gradually raised to start the distillation. Condenser was tap water cooled and the distillation was conducted for 4 h. Optimum hydro distillation time was found to be around 4 h or 240 min for 4 days dried ginger samples according to a recent Indonesian study (
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Hasmita et al., 2015</xref>). Therefore, optimal parameters were used in the current study according to the requirement. Apparatus was let to cool for 15–20 min until the last of the vapors were condensed in to the collecting arm. Hydro extracted essential oil was collected to sample tubes and 0.1 g of anhydrous sodium sulphate was introduced to absorb any trapped moisture. Sample tubes were labeled and stored in cold storage at 4 °C until further analysis. For each variety-location-maturity combination three replicates were collected. A total of 54 (3 × 2×3 × 3) replicates were collected and measured.
</p>
