<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The essential oil was analysed by gas chromatograph directly coupled to a mass spectrometer (MS) Perkin Elmer Inc., Clarus 500 model (Waltham, MA, USA). The GC was equipped with two columns, one of which was a Restek Stabilwax (fused-silica) polar capillary column, and the other was a Varian (VF-1ms) apolar column. Helium was used as carrier gas at a flow rate of 1 mL/min [
 <xref rid="B37-molecules-24-02701" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The Restek column was operated using an injector temperature of 280 °C and the following oven temperature program: Isothermal at 60 °C for 5 min, then ramped to 220 °C at a rate of 5 °C min
 <sup>−1</sup>, and finally isothermal at 220 °C for 20 min. The other apolar column was operated using an injector temperature of 280 °C and the following oven temperature program: Isothermal at 60 °C for 5 min, then ramped to 220 °C at a rate of 5 °C min
 <sup>−1</sup>, a second ramp to 260 °C at a rate of 5 °C min
 <sup>−1</sup> and finally isothermal at 260 °C for 10 min. One microlitre of lavandin EO was diluted in 1 mL of methanol and the injection volume was 1 μL. The injector split ratio was 1:20. Mass spectra were recorded at 70 eV (EI: electronic impact) and were scanned in the range 40–400 
 <italic>m/z</italic>. The GC-TIC (total ion current) mass spectra were obtained by data analysis software (TurboMass
 <sup>TM</sup> GC/ MS PerkinElmer). The LEO constituents were identified by comparison of their linear retention indices (LRIs), (relative to C8–C30 aliphatic hydrocarbons, Ultrasci injected into both polar and apolar columns under the same operating conditions described above) with available retention data in the literature. Further identification of all components was made by matching their mass spectra with those stored in the Wiley and NIST02 mass spectra libraries database. GC-FID (flame-ionization detector) analysis was performed under the same experimental conditions using the polar column as described for the GC–MS measurements. The FID temperature was 280 °C. Relative amounts of the essential oil components were obtained by peak area normalisation without the use of an internal standard or correction factors and expressed in percentages. All analyses were repeated twice.
</p>
