<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">The five most common chemical reaction processes can be applied to convert TAG&#8217;s to FA(X)E, which are thermal cracking, transesterification and/or esterification, superfluid techniques [<xref rid="B15-polymers-14-00210" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>], enzymatic, and Hydrotreated Vegetable Oil (HVO) techniques. HVO can be considered as a hybrid technique, which can result not only in biodiesel but in several final products, and, furthermore, biodiesel originating from HVO is usually not fully compatible with diesel machines without having engine adjustments [<xref rid="B16-polymers-14-00210" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. A chemical cracking process requires high temperatures and expensive equipment. Enzymatic catalysis is difficult to scale up due to pH and temperature sensibility of the enzymes (mainly lipases), and the low solubility in alcohol usually inhibits the enzymatic activity [<xref rid="B17-polymers-14-00210" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. To date, transesterification is the most applied reaction process on the biodiesel industrial scale, being able to convert TAG&#8217;s to FA(X)E within one cycle of reaction with conversion yields to fulfill either ASTM D6751 or EN 14214:2003. Nevertheless, transesterification reaction presents low kinetics velocity and is energetically unfavorable. To enhance reaction velocity, acids or bases are used as a catalyst for optimizing the chemistry process. In reality, the catalyst has to be considered as a must in order to obtain reasonable and efficient conversion yields from TAG&#8217;s to FA(X)E [<xref rid="B7-polymers-14-00210" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,<xref rid="B18-polymers-14-00210" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Catalyst selection is of fundamental relevance for feedstock transesterification. Basic medium reactions using homogeneous alkali catalysts, mainly sodium and potassium hydroxides, present a high-yield conversion of TAG&#8217;s to FA(X)E, with the advantages of being carried out at mild temperatures and having low costs. Nevertheless, it is most suitable for first-generation feedstock, which presents low FFAs and water contents [<xref rid="B19-polymers-14-00210" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="B20-polymers-14-00210" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. As biodiesel production is still carried out in its majority by first-generation feedstock, basic catalysis is the most applied one [<xref rid="B21-polymers-14-00210" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p>