<p xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">OPEr was covalently attached to the insoluble scaffolds using several strategies that involve different structural regions. First, the synthesis of mCLEAs is probably the least specific of the methods used, since proteins are massively precipitated and crosslinked. However, the procedure used here involves a first (probably ionic) interaction of the protein with the AMNP-GA carrier, which conditions the activity of the preparation, since mCLEAs of OPEr synthesized by direct addition of precipitant and crosslinker were inactive in this reaction (data not shown). Second, the immobilization of OPEr by attachment by its oxidized glycidic chains to the AMNP carrier is an unusual method that, as already mentioned, may better preserve enzyme activity. The mobility of the peptide chain should still be restricted due to immobilization, although protein structure and activity are probably less affected than in the other procedures. Finally, the neutral pH used for immobilization of OPEr to the AMNP-GA carrier [<xref rid="B45-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] makes it unlikely that the &#949;-amino groups of surface lysins are activated since their pKa is very high. Under these conditions, it is quite possible that the proteins have joined the activated scaffold mainly by their N-terminal amino acid [<xref rid="B29-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], although we cannot exclude the intervention of other regions with reactive amino groups at neutral pH. Despite the proximity of the N-terminal to the lid region of OPEr [<xref rid="B55-jof-07-00822" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>], it appears that immobilization through this point does not affect its opening, since the immobilized biocatalyst is active. In addition to covalent immobilizations, a commercial magnetic support functionalized with surface octyl groups (SiMAG-octyl<sup>&#174;</sup>) was also used to immobilize OPEr by hydrophobic interaction.</p>